Hello, welcome everyone. It is August
20th at the stroke of zero UTC
on the 21st in 2025 and it's active
inference guest stream 118.1.
We're here with Tatahhiro Tanaguchi and
we'll see a presentation on co-creative
learning via Metropolis Hastings
interaction between humans and AI and
then I will read any questions in the
live chat and ask some things about this
fascinating research. So thank you for
joining again Tadherro and to you for
the presentation.
Okay. Uh thank you very much for
inviting me to this great guest swim
again. So I'm from Ky University and
today I'll be talking about core
creative learning by methics interaction
between humans and AI and this is based
on our preprint which is recently
available on archive. So this is the
cocreative learning is a new theory of
human in the loop machine learning
method. So the I also discuss a
corrective predictive coding hypothesis
which I have I talked in the previous
guest assume maybe you can check it
later but as a background of this work
okay let me start. So uh here here's
here is an overview of our main
contributions of this paper. The first
the we formally propose co-creative
learning and this is a novel paradigm
the way humans and AI collaboratively
achieve symbol emergence in other words
the formation of the external
representation by mutually integrating
uh their partial perceptual information
to build a shared representation.
So this fundamentally shifts the
perspective on human AI alignment or
teaching process moving beyond
traditional unilateral unilateral
approach. The second we introduce an
experimental framework based on the
Metropolis Hastings naming game and
through this framework we propose the
comparing empirical evidence
demonstrating that human AI peers can
effectively engage in this creative
learning process.
So uh the visual the of this right
and illustrates uh the idea of mutual
interaction between the human and the AI
uh centering around the shared world.
Okay. So let's consider why correlate
learning is so crucial currently in in
this at this phase. So the first one is
limitations of unilateral alignment or
teaching. Traditionally unilateral
alignment remark or teaching but
typically supervised learning based on
ground truth levels provided by human
annotators have significant limitations.
For instance, AI systems already excel
beyond the average human performance in
many areas. uh possessing the distinct
and often superior domain knowledge. The
furthermore the human and AI inherently
have heterogeneous knowledge. Our uh our
our ways of understanding and processing
information are fundamentally different.
So when and also when embodied AI agents
start exploring the world autonomously,
it becomes questionable where whether
that we should enforce our existing
human knowledge and values as a sole
ground truth. So we should respect some
in some sense we should respect AI's
perception and our knowledge to bring
our knowledge better status.
Okay, another thing is the birectional
the influence. So actually the large
language models for example actively
impact the human language use and
decision making as shown by recent
studies. This the mutual influence
clearly highlights the limitation of the
perspective of purely one side alignment
strategy teaching strategy. Therefore,
looking beyond the current genative AI
era, it is important that we establish a
new systems theory the principle and the
learning method to achieve a true human
AI symbiotic the symbiosis considering
by directional alignment or teachings
and that can be called co-creative
learning process.
So uh to push on co-creative learning
more intuitively from the machine
learning perspective let's briefly and
roughly review existing traditional uh
unilateral machine learning frameworks.
So the in the most common the insup
supervised or the reinforcement learning
the human's perspective
the
P uh this human perspective can be
written like that the XN human is the
human's observation and SN is a kind of
the uh cross level or description of the
the uh human's uh perceptional
information.
So the we form the the in our society we
form the relationship that between the
the labels and the particial information
in some sense.
So and this is effectively serves as a
ground truth or the target or re reward
the
the source of reward for the AI to learn
from.
The AI's understanding is therefore
fundamentally bounded by the human's
perspective.
So in in contrast in unsupervised or
self-supervised learning the AI agents
learns in isolation inferring knowledge
uh sorry from its our own observations.
In this case, in this case, its
understanding is bounded only by the
limits of its own perceptual data.
So a key takeaway take away from from
both that these traditional approach is
that the only partial information
is a human
or AI is used for the learning process.
So this highrise a critical limitation.
The nether approach fully leverages the
combined uh potentially richer
the
information available when humans and AI
interact. So this bring us to our
proposal the new bilateral frameworks
called creative learning. Here the goal
is not for one agent to teach the other
but for both to engage in bidirectional
message passing through rankage games
and communication to integrate their
partial observations.
So instead of trading one agent's
perspective perspective as a so truth
the running target for the diet that
becomes the true posterior distribution
uh conditioned on the joint observation
of both agents
here X and AI and X human uh this is
crucial distinction. So by integrating
integrating their distinct and partial
information uh this approach allows
emergent shared understanding to surpass
the knowledge uh and uh perception that
either the humans or the AI the AI could
have uh have formed alone.
The diagram on this slide illust
illustrates uh this mutual interaction
and the formation of a joint uh more
complete understanding.
So
and but uh you know how can we do this
that that is a question and before
diving into the today's main topic let
me briefly introduce or review the
corrective predict coding hypothesis
which I proposed last year and gave a
talk in this uh guest stream last time
so uh this hypothesis extends idea of
well-known predictive coding to social
and linguistic phenomena.
So it states that simple systems that
including language are formed through
collective predict coding by humans. In
other words, a human society uh which
can be regarded as symbol emergence
system the systems performing symbol
emergence that technically can be
understood as a social representation
learning system. As a result, the
information of the world may be encoded
in the distributional semantics of our
language. The hypothesis also suggests
that this is why large language models
appear to understand the word they
inherit uh this structure through vast
amount of distributional the distributed
human generated text. By the way, uh the
diagram illustrates this complex process
the where the emergent where the
individual
uh inference and action loop contribute
to an emergent the symbol system that in
turn constraints the organizes
corrective behavior. So let me
illustrate. So the maybe the uh the
explanation was too quick. So let me
illustrate the CPC hypothesis collective
predictive coding process the bridging
the idea of emergent communication and
the predictive coding or free energy
principle. First let's start from the
predict coding or world model learning.
So um there's a person they internally
he uh intern he or she internally has
internal representation of a world
models
and we are uh living uh with action
perception group. So uh this is very
roughly this is very roughly speaking
the inference process but we humans we
are so many and through communication we
form language.
So following a p predictive coding
hypothesis through language game the we
can form language like social the
represent external representations
through the this learning total learning
process. I think through this process we
model and adapt to the world
collectively.
So but here let me take another view
until now we believe we assume that each
person is an independent and autonomous
agent but let's change uh and take
another viewpoint
first language is here language is a
kind of a system
and uh they have sensors or also
actuators That's us. The language uses
utilizes us to model the world through
interaction. From this viewpoint uh we
are subordinate uh to the language
system because this kind of view is of
mentioned in sociology or other social
science area or cultural psychology. So
I think this kind of dual viewpoint is
very interesting to extend our view of
cognition to the social viewpoint and
actually this dual viewpoint actually uh
gave us opportunity gives us opportunity
to formalize this process the from the
viewpoint of free energy principle.
So the based on the genative model
representing a CPC I mean this uh kind
of the the language model let's let's
let's consider a language is a kind of
brain having this these uh sensor sensor
model systems. So the following the
graphical model the proise geneticity
model the describing such kind of
process uh we can define the free energy
in the same way as the normal usual the
free energy principle.
Interestingly
uh that we can uh based on uh okay that
we can naturally uh derive this kind of
formulation and uh interestingly the the
final form can be divided into two
parts.
So the first one is an ordinary
variational free energy term and this is
sum of the variation of free energy of a
number of agents. In addition to that,
an interesting term pops up. We call
this a collective regularization term.
This term tries to align agents external
representations w
and uh uh with each agent internal
representation z. With this time the
problem of minimization individual free
energy free energy becomes a min
minimization of free energy of a single
total system. I think this book can
extend the free energy principle from
the individual to the collective uh
level with a clear relationship to the
emergence of symbol systems or language.
Okay. So the as the simplest in instance
of the theory of collective predicted
coding uh let me introduce the
metropolis hastings naming game which we
previously proposed. It is a type of
language game built on the solid
mathematical foundations. Uh this will
serves as a as a basis of co creative
learning. I will introduce later. Okay
that how does it works? So here's the
ide
per perception phase the speaker and
listener the observe the same object
and infer their interative
representations. We assume joint
attention here which is crucial for
human language acquisition. And next in
communication phase the speaker
proistically utter a name for the
object. The listener then determine if
it accept the naming. The accepted
naming uh or not
uh with a certain probability the
probability depends on the the its
current uh belief state.
uh specifically this probability show
probability as shown in the equation uh
on the slide reflects how well the
listener's belief matches the name
proposed by the speaker. So if a
listener agent does not find the
incoming sign believable it can reject
the proposal naming and this ability to
reject is crucial. The third the
learning phase after the communication
the listener update its internal
parameter are related to representation
learning and naming and finally a turn
taking turn taking step the speaker and
the listener alternate as their role and
the game continues. Overall this is a
very very simple game but importantly
this game has a solid mathematical
basis.
So uh let's dive into the detail. The if
acceptant decision is made according to
this probability, we can mathematically
prove that the naming game is equivalent
to the metal processing algorithm for
basian inference of the shared
representation
that shown the in uh in this figure on
the left. So let's begin the with this
uh graphical model. So here O A and OB
or we can rename this XA or XP the
represent the visual observation of each
agent uh they are uh the agents with the
visual input here but but any kind of
input is okay basically that is uh Z A
and Z B are the internal representations
latent variables we also assume existing
of a variable W which serves as a prior
for these two observations to uh two
internal variables. So if we treat uh W
as a latent variable
this graphical model becomes very
similar to the multimodel or multi- view
a variational autoenccoder or latent
variable models. And if the two agents
brains were directly connected directly
connected and could be uh could could
use the both observations
simultaneously. Yes. Uh this variable
the can be inferred the in the in the
natural way and would encodes the
combined information from both agents
input. However, in reality uh they are
independent cognitive systems.
So the algorithm so let's introduce a
trick that algorithmically we can
decompose the model into two part. So
left hand side agent A and right hand
side is agent B. So and we let's
consider the kind of alternative
the inference the method for this W. Now
think about the sampling process. Agent
A propose propose a candidate of latent
variable WD by sampling from its
posterior distribution
and uh the proposed value is passed to
agent B. The agent B can decide whether
to accept the sample from a sample the
based on certain probability.
So this is this process
is the
uh this process can be designed
that by using the metropolis hastings
algorithm which is uh which is a kind of
march Monte Carlo MCMC.
So actually the under certain conditions
this guarantees that shadow signs are
formed and uh uh and that categorize
categor that uh that categories emerges
among the agent to approximate the
posterior distribution uh based on the
agent's observations.
So and importantly this the what I
explained here is mathematic is uh
completely equivalent to this uh naming
game. So it is proves that this naming
game itself is basian the inference
approximate basian inference procedure.
So this is a very important point this
is very important point. So then in the
previous paper uh we tested uh this idea
on some data set and we showed that the
agent uh two agent playing met naming
game can effectively integrate uh their
the partial information and form the
sign form and share signs
signs I mean the categories the how say
across the agent and Actually such kind
of process even uh even outperform
the learning result achieved by a single
agent.
So the without any ground truth this
kind of method voice hasting interaction
can improve the representation learning
process you know in some sense the
knowledge the formation process.
Okay. So this is the background and uh
actually actually after this the
computation study
you know the we the as as you see as you
saw in my talk I always assume that this
is a this is uh something happening that
in our society human. So uh to to show
that we need to check we need to
validate that if the this kind of things
is happening in human interaction.
So we designed an experiment to test
whether human participant when playing a
game similar to the MH metropolitics
naming game would follow the acceptance
probability calculated uh by the
algorithm.
The results as shown in the graphs on
the right are positive. We found that
the human acceptance behavior indeed the
mostly aligned with the theoretical
theoretically derived image acceptance
probability. This is crucial finding
because it suggests that humans to a
certain extent follow similar patterns
to the metropolis hasting naming game
providing empical support for the idea
that human behavior on simple emergence
might follow a CPC mechanism. Uh this
paves the way for our recent work
integrating AI and human into this
framework. So this is the beginning of
actually today's main topic.
So a simple way to introduce co-creative
learning is to view it through the lens
of a metroping style interaction between
human and AI
like this.
So okay let's jump into uh this section.
So given this insight uh we then move to
the core of our current work the
realization of co collective predictive
coding within a human AI collaborative
system as depicted uh in this graphical
model. We envision
the system where a human and AI agent
uh each with partial observations
engage in bilateral message passing
through language game or communication.
This interaction facilitates the in the
formation and influence of a shared
understand shared representation
and uh represented uh by the QSN. This
is a kind of sign and shared latent
variable and X
AI and X human. This means the AI's
observations and humans observations.
Okay. And this uh is what we define as
co-creative learning. The key idea here
is that uh instead of one agent simply
teaching the other the both mutually
integrates their partial perceptual
information. The display process enable
the enabled the by by the mechanism like
the MH energy metab
allows them to jointly construct a
richer shared external representation
uh that neither could achieve alone and
this is a direct instance
uh in in instantiation
of the CPC hypothesis in a human AI. I
triad.
So more formally to be prepared t we
formally define cocreative learning as
an interactive decentralized via
inference process as shown in in
definition one uh in our in the preprint
the through message based uh message
based update like the metrop game uh
jointly construct uh local belief
distributions S
the crucial aspect is that this process
ensure the expected a corrective energy
fd decreased over interaction steps.
This means that the mar chain formed by
their interactions converges to the true
posterior distribution uh conditioned on
a joint uh observations of the both AI
and the humans. So what's remarkable
about this mechanism is that it allows
for in improvement of multicar multicar
estimates of the evidence p uh x ai uh x
uh human without requiring either agent
to disclose their private observation or
internal gradient. So this decentralized
nature is a key advantage in enabling
robust and private knowledge uh co
construction.
Okay. So with this formal definition in
mind our primary objective for this
experiment uh was to empirically test uh
this concept. We conducted an experiment
where joint attention naming game that
this is a this is a kind of the you know
the uh experiment experiment the with
participants the to asking to play the
play the mage naming game like you know
naming game. So was played that this
this game was played uh between human
participant and the computer agent. The
central question we aim to answer was uh
can the human and the computer
effectively integrate their respective
partial observations through this naming
game. So thereby the engage in the
decentralized basian inference
or as we term it co-creative learning.
To ensure this, the each agent was given
only a partial a missing subset of the
full observation information of
observational information.
As you can see in this diagram, the
human might have certain dimension of
features
and while the agent has others and some
are missing for each. So this setup
makes accurate categorization impossible
based on solely on individual
information thus necessitating
information integration through
communication.
Uh we wanted to see if they could
collaboratively fill in this uh missing
piece and uh reach a shared
understanding.
So uh let's detail
let's detail our material methods the
stimuli consisted on image
images depicting sub with a radial
notch. So these were generated based on
fivedimensional vectors sampled from one
uh of three uh ground truth gausian
distribution
and use using the ci lab space which is
perceptually uniform. So the uh
parameters were chosen so that
categories would overlap significantly
in the partial observation space like
this. The crucially as as shown in
figure uh this fig this
this part
humans and computer agent receive
different partial observations. Human
participants view uh grayscale uh
rendered rendering the based on the
original figure
and uh and uh yeah. Okay. and uh the
and the agent
agent only can see the color
color information. Uh this pass
observability makes accurate
categorization impossible based the
story on individual information.
So making communication essential.
So that datad's task was to collaborate
the categorize these simul into up to
three uh categories. The yes the ABC
by playing the naming game. Uh figure
this side figure B uh illustrates
experimental proced procedure flow the
involving initial categorization in
shadow categorization
and uh and the naming game and uh ro
switching.
So this is actually very difficult task
for human
participant as you can imagine. Okay. Uh
this is a very the this process. The the
slide show a screenshot of the
experimental interface used in our uh
experiment. First participants were
asked to categorize the given images uh
by uh dragging then into lab boxes as
seen on the on the left. The during the
naming game uh one
uh one image is presented on the right
on the right
and the naming agent the propose a name
or sign for the imaging by clicking the
button. The listener then decide uh
whether to accept uh the proposed uh
proposal name by clicking and accept or
reject
sorry the instruction is in Japanese.
The after this decision the listener is
prompted uh to revise their own
categorization if needed.
This intuitive inter interface supports
the partial observation and the sign
exchange uh between the human and
computer agent facilitating the inter
interactive process.
Okay. So the experiment was conducted
online via web browser. We recruited 90
participants through crowd works uh
crowd sourcing service and after
filtering for engagement and uh
adherence to instruction 69 participants
were included in our final analysis. The
experiment typically uh lasted about uh
90 to uh 120 minutes like 2 hours. the
with participants receiving compensation
for their time.
Okay. So for comparison participants
were divided into three distinct group.
So each uh interacting with computer
agent employing a different acceptance
strategy. The for human proposal group
one the image group the metropolis
hastings engaged with an AI that accept
that accepted the proposals based on the
metropolis hastings acceptance
probability
uh serving as our primary co-creative
learning condition. Group two, the
always accept group that interacted with
an AI that always accept proposals
acting as a proxy, a proxy for
traditional supervised learning. You
know, the humans suggestion is always
true.
Finally uh group three the already
reject group the communicated with an AI
that uh the already reject human
proposals the mirroring and unsupervised
learning scenario. So the uh AI just
learn the form categories the from the
observation. These conditions allows us
to uh systematically evaluate the
effectiveness of the MHNG in
facilitating co-creative learning. So uh
let's look at the result for clustering
accuracy measured by uh adjusted randics
ARI. Table one summarizes the initial
and the final mean ARI score for both
human and computer agents across all
groups. A key finding is that the
participants in MH group achieved the
highest categorization accuracy and sign
agreement particularly on the AI side.
uh when compared to both the always
accept and always re reject group. Uh
specifically specifically the computer
agent the in the MH condition a computer
agent in MH condition
uh
achieved a significantly higher final
mean ARI. This clearly indicates that
the image based interaction most
effectively facilitated shared
understanding between human and AI
engaging a more collaborative and
accurate modeling of the world. So while
interacting uh generally helped the
human improve
the uh image mechanism was uh uniquely
effective for the AI agent to leverage
the interaction for super uh superior
performance.
Okay, to visualize this trend in this
figure, figure three plots the mean AI
over the 200 communication steps for
both human and computer agent. uh in the
condition
the you can clearly observe that the the
both the MH and the AA uh all acceptance
are always acceptance condition show a
general trend to increase ARI for both
humans and computer indicating a
successful information integration and
learning the learning from interaction
and uh In uh contrast, the a
condition always reject uh condition
where the AI always reject proposal show
uh relative to no improvement from the
initial categorization accuracy
especially for the computer agent. uh
this graph vividly demonstrate the
superior performance and the running
trajectory achieved under the metropolis
hasting direction particularly uh for
the AI agent.
Okay. Uh beyond the beyond just communic
uh categorization accuracy we also
evaluated the sign posterior
distribution convergence.
So as highlighted the in table one the
MH group achieves the highest
convergence the between the agent's
final sign distribution and the target
posterior distribution derived from the
combined model.
uh this this indicates that uh the MH
based interaction most effectively
guided the diad towards the emergence of
a shared the informative science system
that truly reflect the integrated
information.
Now while human participants in the
image condition also show the high high
agreement
uh the difference compared to the always
accept condition was not uh
statistically significant.
So uh however the AI's performance in
the MH group was significant superior
demonstrating the its ability to
converge the interaction to align its
understanding with the humans uh leading
to a richer shared the representation as
indicated by the convergence toward the
s given x ai and xuma
to summarize our discussion
The experiments clearly show that the
human AI pair can successfully engage in
cogreative learning via the joint
attention naming game. So uh under
partial observation the metropolis
hastings acceptance rule significantly
improve categorization accuracy and
agreement that compared to both always
accept and always reject control
conditions. uh this is evident in the AR
I graph AI graph and the sign agreement
score we just discussed. Furthermore, a
crucial finding was that the human
acceptance behavior aligned uh closely
with the theoretically derived metrop
Hastings probability as shown in figure
four. this figure
uh this reinforces the idea that the
mechanis mechanism enhances a p
perceptual integration and effectively
facilitates decentralized basia
inference within human AI diet. The deal
findings collectively suggest a
promising direction of the designing
truly symbiotic AI systems system that
run with human by fostering the emergent
so uh interactiondriven alignment moving
beyond the limitation of the traditional
unilateral unilateral approach uh to the
to to AI development.
Okay. So while uh our findings are
highly promising, we acknowledge several
limitations in our current studies that
we utilized actually simple the
artificial gen artificially generated
visual stimuli and categorical signs. So
this control setup was necessary for
initial validation I believe but uh it
naturally limits the generalizability of
our findings to complex the complex real
world tasks involving richer semantics
and natural language uh such as those
handled by large language models. The
additionally our joint attention naming
game paradigm assumes a perfect joint
attention between agent. So in real
world interactions the attentional
alignment can fail. So which is an
important uh important aspect for future
research. And looking ahead we identify
several key future challenges. Uh these
include uh scale uh scaling to richer
modality and semantics robustness to
imperfect attention uh designing real
time coive system and understanding
emerging dynamics in large scale systems
and al also ethical and uh
interpretability concern is also
important I think so and uh actually the
to build the a truly symbol otic uh
human AI society. So how do how to
integrate this kind of idea to the
practical applications? That is also
important topic. Okay. Uh that's all
from my side. I thank you very much for
your attention and I look forward to
further discussion. Okay. Thank you very
much.
Thank you for the talk. Awesome.
All right.
I will ask a few questions that I wrote
and I will copy them into the chat as
well. And for anyone in the live chat,
please feel free to write questions and
I'll copy them in. All right. So, first
comment and question.
The task focused on categorical discrete
as well as quantitative aspects of
situational semantics played via a
language game related to sharing
information about a shape in a shared
world.
What kinds of AI human tasks do you
think this kind of algorithm could be
used for? For example, do you see it in
the domain of the text chat or a robotic
setting or just in other words,
>> which application directions do you find
promising or most able to demonstrate
the differences and strengths of the
framework compared with the unilateral
supervised or unsupervised learning
systems?
>> Yeah, thank you very much uh for great
questions. there actually that I should
ask that I should add the in
explanation. So actually the maybe that
this this experiment itself looks very
uh how say simple and categorical
categorical uh sign information and uh
this but uh now what I want to uh show
in this uh talk and in this paper is the
kind of the very the basic uh basic
validation of this approach creative
learning. So and uh this kind of this
graphical model and this setting is not
limited to the categorical setting and
also the you know the uh small number I
I mean the uh
simple uh visual image and actually so
as I mentioned what I did is uh swapping
the one agent in this the kind of the
naming a language game the swapping the
by swapped by the by a human
participant. So actually this kind of
approach collective predictive coding
based approach is now the extending to
many domains. So uh let me share the
okay so it's a kind of appendix slide.
So actually this uh uh approach was
extended to the multiple agent and uh
also the multi- aent reostment running
and also the importantly the you know
this is also another blueprint we
recently shared. So this approach uh can
be extended to the more complex tasks.
So uh this is uh for example this this
paper uh is dealing with uh the kind of
the captioning game not the naming game
captioning game. So between the two
visual language model agent you know the
one agent receives a a natural image and
describe it in the natural language.
Okay. So they receive the another agent
receive the text. text is just a picture
you know a sequence of uh categorical
variables and that can be uh treated in
our framework in a in a similar way. So
actually that we showed that uh this
kind of process improve uh has
successfully integrate the two agents
the knowledge of the vision lage models.
So I think we are now we are as many uh
researches now ongoing. So I think that
we can uh I believe uh we can extend
this idea to the large language model
setting and also that we can uh say that
now as you know currently in robotics
field visual language action model
visual language action model is
gathering attention. So maybe we can uh
consider the how can we the extend this
idea to such kind of robotic scenario as
well.
Awesome.
Um
okay, next question and then I'll read
from the chat. Okay.
How do you see this in terms of
converging to a shared stable truth
versus situations of novelty like
cocreation of art or research where
there's not necessarily a pre-existing
ground truth even of a latent kind to
converge to. I'm thinking about
situations where the agent models have
overlapping information which is
redundant though robust
or non-over overlapping information
which is useful though fragile and then
also information that maybe neither
agent has. So, h how do you adapt the
situation
to to tune whether you're looking to
kind of find an existing compromise
versus move into a third space that
might be different than what either
agent has or knows.
Thank you very much for your great
question and actually that's very very
very uh interesting uh topic and uh
interesting interesting uh discussion
point. So actually the mathematically
speaking so if the if they don't have
the shared information sh I mean the you
know the uh observation
the contain does not contains shared the
information. So it's very difficult to
uh I I I I expect that the it's very
difficult to form the shared uh
representations
and uh reach agreement in some sense. So
and uh but uh the it's very and but I
didn't have I don't have the empirical
evidence about that on the with some
experiment but I think that this is now
is very important uh step to conduct an
constructive studies studies to analyze
such kind of what kind of phenomena
happens with uh this kind of you know
basic mechanism
for emergence and the formation of
shared the representation and also now
maybe the this is a kind of the somehow
a bit outside of the today's topic but I
think that this kind of scenario can be
find uh in the democratic discussion in
our society as well. So the I think the
one of my student is working on the the
topic about the relationship between
collective political coding and
democracy and digital democracy.
So the if the two agents uh don't have
the shared experience uh it's very
difficult to have to reach or to reach
agreement and also the you know the
diff very if they have a very different
belief system the it's uh it's the will
I say it will become very difficult to
agree. So then that such kind of thing
this this kind of mechanism is somehow
existing the behind the curtain of the
current the social division
or system. Yeah, I think that the
currently I'm very interested in the
connection between the you know this
kind of computational research and the
simple emergence representation learning
stuff things and the social science uh
topics as well. Thank you very much.
>> Yes, that makes a lot of sense. I guess
just speculatively if two agents are in
a shared environment
with a simple optima to be reached or at
least a gradient to be followed at least
there's a norm to which the gradient
could be followed or local or global
optima could be reached. But if you have
agents that are in two different
environments,
>> you kind of lose even the possibility of
a guarantee
because if it's like if two people are
in two different rooms with two
different temperatures
>> Mhm.
>> there's no guarantee they would converge
to the same air conditioning.
>> Mhm.
>> But if they were in the same room with a
shared air conditioning, at least they
could.
Yeah. Okay. Oh yeah, go ahead.
>> I think very it's very interesting to
think over the kind of the how can we
how uh should we in how can we improve
the design of communication and how can
we how uh should we uh consider the the
envir the difference of environment
uh to the achieve the mutual to you know
uh to
how say to understand the mutual their
understanding between uh two or more
agents something like that. Sorry.
>> Yeah.
>> Sorry.
>> I'll read a question from the live chat.
If if anyone else has a live chat
question, they should write it. So
Frederick Kintanar wrote, "In your
model, how do you approach the
difference between the way silicon
agents and humans model the concept
level of words in context?
AI is opaque. How can this be improved
for interpretability?
>> Okay, thank you very much. That's also
very much important point. The in our
framework the most important part of our
framework is uh uh that uh we totally
deal different how say totally deal with
a system kind of decentralized system.
So the in the one of the most important
part of this mechanism we the each agent
uh need not look into the the the
internal phenomena now of the
counterpart agents. So the even in the
computer agent settings the what the
agent a do is just a kind of the uh
utter the giving sign to speak something
and listen and uh and determine the if
it to accept or not by itself. So, so
the there is no you know there is no
need to uh kind kind of look into the
other agent variables you know so the so
this you know the actually the in the
similar studies in emergent
communication some many studies uh how
say uh ask to pass the kind of the
gradient of the parameter through agents
you know so across agents it's
impossible for human but but uh in this
setting uh we don't need to do that so
actually that in this mechanism we just
consider the counterpart agent as a
black box so what we did in this
framework is is in concrete learning is
just swapping the blackbox by human
agent
and just expect the human human behavior
follows the maming game based mechanism
algorithm. So actually so uh to that end
uh to validate that so we did conducted
uh this experiment previously and we
somehow found that the human in this
kind of setting human actually follow
the image algorithm to some extent and
also the in this experiment again again
we uh checked that uh the human behavior
is similar to the MH algorithm and as a
result that we can expect actually
expect that the total the correct pre-
energy uh can be discre decreased
uh through this interaction that is a
scenario and uh regarding the
explanability
that is a very how say the difficult
question and we need to consider and uh
but
you know but uh in uh in the uh how say
in the series of studies of explanable
AI. So the definition of explanability
as is how say
very somehow uncertain you know the
pleasure and and actually the uh explain
I'll say uh even the in the current
large language model the explanability I
mean the what happening inside of the
neural network is a very challenging
problem And uh how say the human
how say
in I think that the similar problem can
be found in this scenario as well. But
uh anyway so when we introduce uh this
kind of idea idea to our society
uh we assume that uh uh a a
uh not just a follower of or students of
human. So the human can be affected
human decision can be affected uh by AI.
So maybe the of course that we need to
reconsider the escal issues and uh
explanability uh based on such kind of
assumptions.
Sorry the
the my answer is not perfect but yeah
that's comment from my side.
>> Great. Okay. And one more
question I wrote in a comment in the
chat. So
>> you mentioned different ways of
communication amongst AI, human AI and
human humid diads and groups and I think
the relevance of understanding and
modeling and creating high integrity
settings for these communications is
clear. So what might these communication
strategies look like? For example, let's
assume that we can do realtime language
translation between mother tongues like
Japanese or English. From there, what
kinds of games might be possible? For
example, would that high bandwidth
communication still look like how are
you doing? What are you up to? Or could
there be some structured communication
games like captioning or joint
classification
which could engage shared attention in
ways that were previously impossible and
discover new global free energy optima
uh
thank you very much for your questions.
I'm now
h and uh try to grasp the point we can
do real time language translation
mother like uh from there what kind of
game
>> if everyone could speak and hear in the
natural language that was most
comfortable to them what would be the
semantics of the language games that
would support high bandwidth
communication.
High bandwidth communication.
Uh you mean the
the so what what what does the real time
language translation
means here? So everyone can this means
everyone can understand. So what?
>> You can speak you can speak in Japanese
and hear what I'm saying in Japanese
and I'll hear what you say in English
and I could speak in English. So we're
using some AI system to auto translate
what we hear and say
in close to real time so that so we can
have a natural conversation with our
mother tongues.
So then
I'm just kind of curious and and
wondering
whether then we would have a sort of
normal like on the street conversation
or whether your work is providing some
situations or structured games
like kind of like language chess
where we could play a game together like
captioning
or classification
that could be used to reduce the free
energy on a joint distribution
in a way that would be like faster or
different than just asking about your
day or your friends or your family.
Okay, thank you for your question and uh
I'm not still uh I'm not sure if I got
get the the point clearly but the
basically the I know imaging game the
naming game or captioning game uh this
is kind of a very very small subset of
what the what's happening in our total
language game the in our society so the
the actually bas Basically the our
assumption is that the our assumption or
our uh idea is that the the language the
the formation of language or symbol
emergence itself is a part of the
adaptation to the environment and uh you
know that's totally somehow same as uh
collective uh the predictive coding and
uh active inference.
And uh so the the you know so I I I I
don't have an answer to this uh question
uh but uh uh how say so
you know the we share some task we share
some task or some environment if we are
human the that's task so maybe gradually
the our way of communication
uh gradually change and optimize uh to
the uh to the shared task or shared
environment the that's my idea and I
don't know the kind of the I don't know
the connection with the the real time
translation uh how say the the
discussion point so
is it okay I don't know
>> sorry I I think it's uh a mystery for us
and others to explore in the future.
Like if we were fluent,
>> Mhm.
>> in hearing and speaking to everybody,
what would we talk about? Like if we
knew every language perfectly and we
could communicate to to everyone and
everyone could be included in the
conversation,
>> would that conversation look like just
meeting somebody at the bus stop? Or I
think your work provides some structured
settings
where the information content of
communication
could be quantitatively analyzed
and different contributions and
proposals could be understood in terms
of how they contribute to co-alignment.
Um okay and
>> think of it.
>> Yes, last question.
So what are your next research
directions or questions and what
milestones or developments from your
group and colleagues or in the broader
AI space are you looking out for?
>> Okay. Uh thank you very much. The in the
relation with the development of AI
system. So the one thing is that uh how
can we uh integrate uh this idea into LM
the agent systems and the BM and the
vision action model and actually so one
of the you know the the for the
basically the you know CPC the original
idea is uh CPC and the simple emerging
systems. So the I I would like to uh
jump out the from this kind of agent
viewpoint but uh I think that this is
crucial to consider the how can we how
can we form the language system or
shared the belief system together with
other agent. I think it's crucial for
human intelligence I think and the
cognition I think and uh the the and
from this viewpoint we can I think we
can integrate the human and AI and robot
uh to this system. So and that can bring
us to the next step of AI human and AI
the symbiotic society. So that is
important point and the first step one
step is to the make the this kind of
system work the with AI and robot I mean
that you know I showed the BM the
image captioning game system. So
actually that's actually imp improve the
performance of BM
and uh also that I can I think the area
that can can be uh say the you know the
kind of the decentralized or much agent
system can be uh reformulated from this
viewpoint and also and uh we can put the
human agent uh to such such kind of
ecosystems you know. So uh of course the
human area interaction
uh can take time and uh and through that
process so
can learn from the human participants
the you know adaptively but at the same
time so inevitably human agents can be
be affected by M's output
but in In many discussion this kind of
the phenomena is regarded as just a bias
or bias somehow the bias is constant to
be considered a negative thing negative
thing but you know the such kind of bias
can be regarded as a kind of the
knowledge the from AI agent as well. So
the we I think that the the the most
important one of the most important next
step is to formalize this kind of
interaction from the viewpoint of the
collective free energy minimization and
the language image like language game
and uh you know produce the the kind of
qualitatively different the human AI AI
uh system and that uh hopefully
guarantee the co-creative process and
that is the most important uh step uh
forward. Yes, thank you very much.
Thank you. A great way to end it.
I really appreciated the presentation.
I think that the comparison of
supervised or unsupervised learning
makes it clear that both of the
unilateral
frameworks have fundamental limitations
and that a co-creative path
is a great joint distributional future.
Thank you very much. Thank you. Okay,
till next time.
See you.